Methodology

To construct our analysis, we applied an assortment of rhetorical tags to the discourse files of the candidates. These tags account for the rhetorical techniques that the candidates use during their interviews and and speeches. Taking into account the topics that the candidates address, these rhetorical techniques shed light on how the candidates appeal to their respective voter base and attempt to attract those who might not normally favor their party. Where foreign countries are concerned, we can learn how particular parties profess to approach foreign relations. This is of particular interest given the tense relationship that Russian currently has with the United States and many European countries.

Rhetorical devices

To best understand how each politician talks to the general public, we decided to develop a system for annotating rhetorical tags, adapted from van Dijk's framework for ideological discourse analysis in “Politics, Ideology, and Discourse”. His classification system for CDA is based on the “ideological square” that describes the general aims of ideological discourse:

emphasize our positives
emphasize opponents' negatives
de-emphasize our negatives
de-emphasize their positives

To better understand the rhetorical tags and how they have been applied in other research, we looked at Rashidi and Souzandehfar's critical discourse analysis of the debates around the Iraq War. Although their analysis was applied to a specific topic, war, it gave us ideas on how to extend van Dijk's theory by tracking the targets of certain devices, the truth of arguments, and sentiment of certain descriptions.

Some of these rhetorical devices were not applicable to the project. For example, the candidates did not use statistics often in their arguments, so we decided to merge it with the “evidence” rhetorical device. We also added two rhetorical device tags to better describe how Putin and Zhirinovskii talk. In the process of reading, we discovered that both candidates tell stories or anecdotes to make their points. The candidates will occaisionally make explicit assumptions in their speeches, and we wanted to capture this as well.

Rhetorical device
from van Dijk
homebrewed | XML Tag | Description | Example
Actor Description | <ru:actorDesc> | The <evidence> tag marks when the speaker describes an individual or group. We marked whether the sentiment was positive, negative, or neutral. | Соединенные Штаты везде по всем миру активно вмешиваются в выборные кампании других стран.
target: United States
sentiment: negative
Anecdote | <ru:anecdote> | The <anecdote> tag marks when the speaker uses a story as part of their argument. | Мы с Вами вчера встречались вечером, мы с Вами сегодня целый день вместе работали, сейчас опять встречаемся. Когда я пришёл на мероприятие нашей компании Russia Today и сел за стол, рядом сидел какой-то господин с одной стороны, с другой стороны кто-то ещё сидел, потом я выступил, ещё о чём-то поговорили, я встал и ушёл. И потом мне сказали: « Вы знаете, это американский гражданин, он тем-то занимался, он раньше в спецслужбах работал, а теперь он занимается тем-то и тем-то». Я сказал: « Ну и хорошо, вы с ним как-то сотрудничаете?» – « Нет, мы его просто пригласили как одного из гостей». Я говорю: « Ну молодцы, слава богу». Всё! Я с ним даже практически не разговаривал. Я с ним только поздоровался, сел рядом, потом попрощался, встал и ушел. Всё моё знакомство с господином Флинном.
Assumption | <ru:assumption> | The <assumption> tag marks when the speaker explicitly makes an assumption in their argument. | Если бы было что-нибудь выдающееся, из ряда вон выходящее, он бы, конечно, доложил министру, министр – мне.
Authority | <ru:authority> | The <authority> tag marks when the speaker references an authority. We also annotated what sources the politicians referenced. | Мы говорили об этом и с бывшим Президентом Обамой, мы говорили с некоторыми другими официальными лицами – никто никогда не предъявил мне никаких прямых доказательств. Когда мы говорили с Президентом Обамой на этот счёт, это Вам лучше у него спросить, думаю, что он Вам скажет, что он тоже уверен в этом, но, когда мы с ним говорили, я увидел, что и он засомневался. authority: President Obama
Categorization | <ru:cat> | The <cat> tag marks when the speaker assigns an individual to a group. We identified both the target of categorization, and the group to which they were assigned. |
Consensus Building | <ru:consensus> | The <consensus> tag marks when the speaker identifies with a group, usually to curry political favor. | Обязательно. У нас все возрастные…
Disclaimer | <ru:disclaimer> | The <disclaimer> tag marks when the speaker presents an idea as positive, only to reject it later. |
Evidence | <ru:evidence> | The <evidence> tag marks when the speaker uses supposed evidence to prove a point. We marked whether the evidence was true, false, or unknown. | В Европе взрывают, в Париже взрывают, в России взрывают, в Бельгии взрывают, война идёт на Ближнем Востоке – вот о чём надо думать
truth: true
Hyperbole | <ru:hyperbole> | The <hyperbole> tag marks when the speaker exaggerates meaning by making questionable or absurd assumptions. | Вы думаете, что у меня есть время каждый день общаться с нашими послами во всём мире, что ли?
Implication | <ru:implication> | The <implication> tag marks when the speaker infers implicit information in making his/her argument. | И у этого кандидата тоже были свои политические оппоненты и противники.
Irony | <ru:irony> | The <irony> tag marks when the speaker says one thing but means something else, usually using sarcasm. | Вы просто, знаете что: вы такие изобретательные люди там, такие молодцы. Вам скучно жить, видимо.
National Self-Glorification | <ru:glory> | The <glory> tag marks when the speaker tries to represent him/herself in a positive light by glorifying Russia. | Я чувствую прямую живую связь с этой землёй, с историей, со страной.
Vagueness | <ru:vague> | The <vague> tag marks when the speaker blurs the lines between fact and fiction. | Кто это нам говорит, кто это обижается на нас за то, что мы вмешиваемся? Вы сами постоянно вмешиваетесь.

The occurence of these tactics throughout political discourse indicates the types of strategies that politicians employ to marshal support. We aggregated occurences of these devices in each candidates' speech to characterize the sample of interviews and speeches we chose. Since the sample was so small, driven by a short deadline and the convenience of marking up existing official transcripts, we don't claim that this sample is characteristic of the candidates' rhetoric in general.

Topic Modelling

As a secondary tool in this project, we constructed a topic model using Mallet's LDA module to help us quantify what Putin and Zhirinovskii talked most about in our sample. To remove topically meaningless words, we borrowed a stop word list from a research project that analysed international diplomacy between Russia, Abkhazia, and South Ossetia. In general, we found this list to be less than satisfactory, as it did not stop on posessive pronouns. It also stopped on words that are very uncommon in spoken Russian, but we decided to leave them in because they weren't words that held much meaning. We decided to stop on all posessive pronouns except наш, because it held some meaning in terms of patriotism and otherness.

In addition to removing stop words, we lemmatized the texts using Yandex's Mystem project. We chose to use Mystem over other options for lemmatization, such as the NLTK stem module, because Mystem uses context clues to figure out the role of the word in the sentence, providing better results. In some cases, Mystem returned multiple lemmas for each word along with a weight, or estimated probability that lemma was correctly chosen. After verifying that Mystem gave good results in the case of ambiguity, we decided to take the lemma with the greatest weight.

After these pre-processing steps, we ran Mystem on our documents, experimenting with topic counts between 10 and 60. We found that 30 topics yielded the best results.

For those who haven't used topic modelling before in their own research, it is important to note that topic models provide an approximation of topics that would be understood by a human. For example, a topic might include words like "конфликт", "вооруженный", "cирия", and "ракеты" but it might also include neutral words like "говорить" and "думать". Since the computer model doesn't understand what a military topic looks like, but "говорить" often co-occurs with these military terms, it may be grouped in with the topic.

Results

Premise

The goal of the research was exploratory in nature and the use of topic modeling is a suitably open-ended means to that end. The results yielded a mixture of word lists that compile the most commonly spoken words from the least to the greatest with an individual total for each word. The lists are divided into several categories to include the economy, diplomacy, election interference, Syria, and quality of life.

Limitations

It is essential to note the limited source material and its impact on the results and analysis. Due to the limitations of time and manpower, a total of 5 Putin texts and 3 Zhirinovskii texts were chosen. A small sample such as this should not be taken as broadly representative of Russian political discourse or even of the two candidates themselves. Politicians adapt to the contemporary political climate and address topics that suit the preferences of their audiences. Their topics and tactics may very well change significantly in six months. The explanatory of a topic model is extremely limited given the limited sample size. In this case, we used it as a proof of concept. That is, it has yielded some limited positive results, so if we choose to work futher on the project as the political situation changes, it may prove useful for a bigger sample size. As a result of these limitations, we decided to forgo comparative analysis and focus instead on the overall characteristics of the candidates in the context of the 2018 election.

Results

The percentages that indicate relevancy of particular topics to either candidate are very close and only on the topic of Syria is there a notable contrast with Zhirinivskii above Putin by about 8 perent. The greatest attention was paid to quality of life and Syria and both topics were far ahead of the rest. That the candidates would discuss Syria more than most other topics is not surprising given the prominence of warfare in the country and foreign military involvement. Russia's military involvement and its rivalry with the United States are a significant topic in politics as is the case in the US. Quality of life was not expected to be among the most addressed. Although this could be a result of the limited sample size, this may indicate a general concern among voters about a declining living standard.

Putin's Rhetorical Style

Party platform

The Ediniaja Rossija party platform sums up Putin's goals and interests best. Mataintaining national unity and independence, and ensuring stability are first and foremost in Putin's rhetoric. Even today, Putin's rhetoric reminds the Russian people of the economic chaos during the 1990's, and implicitly reminds them of his success in stabilizing and bringing prestige back to the country. In doing so, he reminds us that economic conditions are still very difficult, but in these conditions he has been able to guarantee some growth (<1% GDP growth per year). In foreign policy, Putin ignores the actions he's taken to worsen relations with the West, rather saying that he's open to cooperation (for example, in Syria), but the West refuses.

Scholarly characterization

Rhetorically, Putin has been described as blending elements of populism and scripted propaganda to defend his rule. Rather than engage with conspiracy theories himself, he alludes to them. One such common conspiracy theory in the Russian political sphere is that the United States wanted to break up Russia after the Soviet Union collapsed. [source] In speeches, he often alludes to Russia's glory days, bringing glory upon himself by lauding the annexation of Crimea as a holy crusade for the place where Vladimir I, the first prince of Kievan Rus', converted to Christianity. Often, he uses anecdotes or evidence that is inherently unverifiable to bolster his arguments. In cases where he might feel trapped by an interviewer, he will draw a false equivalence between the West and Russia. [source]

Putin Rhetorical Devices, count

Putin lyubit nas!

Putin Topics, pct relevance

Zhirinovskii's Rhetorical Style

Party Platform

As stated in the party program and reinforced by much of Zhirinovskii's rhetoric both in our corpus, and in quotations throughout his career, the LDPR is interested in security and social stability above all else. The party, if they are successful in elections, promises to rapidly expand the military-industrial base in order to achieve full employment and quick economic growth.

Scholarly characterization

Zhirinovskii is also widely considered to be a populist, Russian nationalist, and strong supporter of the Orthodox Church. At times, he has proposed radical measures like building a border wall on the Caucasus to keep out Muslims. [source] He has also made brash comments threatening to carpet bomb Poland and the Baltic countries. [source] Much like other populist politicians, he has an authoritarian streak, making proposals to re-institute autocracy and adopt Imperial Russian symbols.

The topic modeling results of Zhirinovskii's rhetoric strongly suggests a preference for evidence as a means to support his claims. This contrasts with Putin's rhetorical style which displays a much more varied strategies. Another point of note is Zhirinovskii's use of polarization as a tactic to rally voter support. This is not surprising given his party's stance on Russian nationalism though it is important to note that Zhirinovskii uses this tactic most frequently with references to foreign entities. Western countries and leaders are the most common targets. Using foreign entities as adversaries is a useful tactic to rally the greatest number of voters to one's own cause without alienating potential voters. This is rather contrary to Putin's party "United Russia" which, as the name implies, strives to build the greatest possible concensus. The military and quality-of-life dominated the discourse of both candidates and that the military would be a prominent topic is not surprising given the contentious relationship between Russian and the west at this time. However, the quality-of-life topic was unanticipated and could reflect the public's concern over their job security and a possible decline of their living standard. The LDPR has a reputation for their promotion of a strong military and Zhirinovskii has made threats of military action in neighbooring countries. Both candidates, despite there divergent platforms, recognized which topics to emphasize during their campaigns and their coincidence is indicative of a wide concern across party lines. Normally, parties present the issues that most concern their own interests and appeal to a particular segment of the population though that appears to be waning recently. The economy and political issues appear to be taking a backseat to the military confrontation with the west and a possibly declining living standard. This could be indicative of a general trend toward political unity in Russia while, conversely, the western nations appear to be fracturing politically.

Zhirinovskii Rhetorical Devices, count

Zhirinovskii Topics, pct relevance

Bibliography

2018 Russian Elections

Vladimir Putin/ Владимир Путин

Vladimir Putin has had a long career spaning 16 years as a KGB agent and has since retired and entered politics where he has remained ever since. He served 2 consecutive terms as President of Russian from 2000 to 2008,one term as prime minister from 2008 to 2012, a third term from 2012 to 2018, and has been elected in 2018 for a fourth term. He has been a member of the Unity and United Russian parties during his political career and pursued a policy of general economic liberalism, formation of economic ties with other eurasian nations such as China, and an adversarial relationship with western governments. According to Russian-based polls, he enjoys a large approval rate among the population with numbers over 70% often cited.

Vladimir Zhirinovski/Владимир Жириновски

Vladimir Zhirinovskii is the leader of the LDPR party(Liberal Democratic Party of Russia) and has run for the presidency five times. He has sought to form an opposition party to the status quo though has had very limited success. Zhirinovsky is well know for his nationalistic views, outspokenness, and anti-western opinions. His party advocates a strong economic interventionist policy while still allowing private ownership of property. The party claims to oppose the communism of the Soviet Union while still advocating the restoration of historical Russian borders which requires the reabsorption of former soviet states such as Belarussia and the Ukraine.

Pavel Grudinin/Павел Грудинин

Pavel Grudinin is a politician and entrepreneur who was the Communist Party's presidential candidate in 2018. He worked at the Lenin State Farm as a mechanic and later formed a private company called ZAO Lenin State Farm. He has since served three terms as a deputy of the Moscow Oblast Duma. The policy of his party is the restoration of socialism with marxism and leninism as the guiding ideologies.

Welcome!

This project showcases our analysis of presidential campaign rhetoric in the 2018 Russian Elections. We analysed the rhetorical devices used by the candidates, as well as the topics which they discuss most commonly in their speeches and interviews.

Contributors

Richard Fulop

Richie is a 4th-year undergraduate at the University of Pittsburgh studying Computer Science and Russian. On this project, he took the lead on the programming aspect of the project, and wrote a lot of the code that works behind the scenes to help analyse and understand the corpus. After graduation in Fall 2018, Richie plans to pursue a career using both his skills with language and technology.

Matt Murphy

Matt is also a 4th-year undergraduate who is pursuing a degree in Russian language and minoring in Korean language. He suggested the topic of Russian political discourse and took the lead on writing the majority of the web content for the pages in English and Russian. He plans to find a career in foreign intelligence using foreign languages.

Ian Loughney

Ian is a 4th-year undergraduate at the University of Pittsburgh studying Linguistics and pursuing a certificate in Russian and Eastern European studies. He took on the design of the website on this project as well as working with Richie on the design of the critical discourse analysis. Upon graduation Ian plans to pursue a career in applied linguistics.